立体声不是机器人可用于确定其3D结构的唯一技术
Stereo is not the only technique that a robot can use to determine the 3D structure of its
世界。这是一个非常熟悉的设备;它是MicrosoftKinect传感器。这有时候
world. This is a very familiar device; it's the Microsoft Kinect Sensor. This is sometimes
称为RGBD相机，它是一个传感器，可以在每个像素处返回红色值，
called an RGBD camera that is it's a sensor that returns you at each pixel, the red value,
绿色值，蓝色值和深度。所以，我们之前谈到了彩色飞机
the green value, the blue value and the depth. So, we talked earlier about color planes in
一个图像。Kinect传感器返回带有4个平面的图像，R，G，B和D.Kinect
an image. The Kinect Sensor returns an image with 4 planes, R, G, B and D. The Kinect
包含2个完全独立的子系统。第一种是相当传统的颜色或
contains 2 quite separate subsystems. The first is a fairly conventional color or
RGB相机。第二部件是激光图案投影仪。所以，这实际上是省略，
RGB camera. The second component is a laser pattern projector. So, this is actually omitting,
一个红外光模式到现场，然后，有一个红外摄像头
a pattern of infrared light onto the scene and then, there is an infrared camera which
正在观察该图案并从图案的观察中，它可以确定三维
is observing that pattern and from the observation of the pattern, it can determine 3-dimensional
结构体。这种模式是什么样的？它的外观
structure. What does this pattern looks like? It's looks
非常斑点，它非常接近随机的点状图案。
pretty speckly, It’s pretty close to a random pattern of dots.
Kinect传感器所做的是利用一种称为结构化的非常经典的原理
What the Kinect Sensor does is exploit a very classical principle called structured
光。我想在这里做的是说明经典结构光的原理
light. What I want to do here is to illustrate the principles of a classical structured light
传感器。此处的灰色框表示Kinect传感器
sensor. The grey box here represents the Kinect Sensor
我们有一个距离传感器一定距离的物体。我们有一台相机
and we have an object at some distance away from the sensor. We have a camera which is
这里用针孔相机模型表示，后面有一个图像平面，我们有
represented here by a pin hole camera model with an image plane behind it and we have
一个发射光线的激光投影仪。那些光线与物体和形状相交
a laser projector which emits a fan of rays. Those rays intersect the object and forms
物体上的光点。相机观察那些光点并形成一个图像
spots of light on the object. The camera observes those spots of light and forms an image which
是那些斑点在物体上的投影。我们只是制作一个临时副本
is a projection of those spots on the object. Let's just make a temporary copy of where
那些斑点在图像平面上。现在，我们将考虑对象已经移动
those spots are on the image plane. Now, we're going to consider that the object has moved
离相机越远，我们重复这个过程。激光投影仪发射
further away from the camera and we repeat the process. The laser projector emits the
相同的激光束风扇。在物体上形成斑点。针孔相机观察到了这一点
same fan of laser beams. Spots are formed on the object. Pinhole camera observes that
我们在图像平面上看到一个投影。如果我们加回前一个图像平面投影
and we see a projection on the image plane. If we add back the previous image plane projection
我们之前说过，我们可以看到点的图案已经移动了。有一个垂直位移
which we say before, we can see that the pattern of dots has moved. There is a vertical displacement
或与物距成比例的差异。
or a disparity that is proportional to the object distance.
因此，这是结构光的基本原理。现在，我们可以添加一些额外的测量
So, this is the fundamental principle of structured light. Now, we can add some additional measurements
这里。我们有一条基线，它是激光投影仪中心之间的距离
here. We have a base line which is the distance between the centre of laser projector and
相机的中心。相机有一个焦距和物体
the centre of the camera. The camera's got a focal length and the object
是在距离z。现在，我们可以写出所有这些数量和差异之间的关系
is at a distance z. Now, we can write a relationship between all of these quantities and the disparity
与物距z成反比。
is inversely proportional to the object distance z.
所以，这并不是Kinect的工作原理，但它是一个非常相似的原理。在
So, this is not exactly how the Kinect works but it's a very similar principle. On the
Kinect传感器本身，基线则是中心之间的距离
Kinect Sensor itself, the base line then is the distance between the centre of the
激光图案投影仪和红外摄像机的中心。另一个原则是
laser pattern projector and the centre of the infrared camera. Another principle is
什么叫飞行时间相机，我们在这里看到的是相机镜头
what's called the time of flight camera and what we can see here is a camera lens in the
中间和两侧，有2个相当高功率的发光阵列
middle and on the either side of that, there are 2 arrays of quite high power light-emitting
二极管。这些二极管不会将散斑图案投射到场景上。他们提供一般
diodes. These diodes don't project a speckle pattern onto the scene. They provide general
场景的整体照明。这个原理就是这样的。该
overall illumination of the scene. The principle works something like this. The
被发射的光以某种相当高的频率被调制并被反射
light that's being emitted is modulated at some quite high frequency and is reflected
关闭物体并由相机拾取。因此，光的调制频率可能
off the object and picked up by the camera. So, the modulation frequency of light might
像10或20兆赫兹。如果我们根据时间绘制光的强度，
be something like 10 or 20 megaHertz. If we plot the intensity of a light against time,
红色的出射光和蓝色的入射光，我们看到入射光是
the outgoing light in red and incoming light in blue, we see that the incoming light is
相对于出射光稍微延迟。
slightly delayed with respect to the outgoing light.
有一个相移。所以，有一个延迟T.距离与
There is a phase shift. So, there's a delay of T. The distance is proportional to the
输出光和入射光之间的相位差。之间的关系
phase difference between the outgoing and the incoming light. The relationship between
这里给出距离和时间延迟T，其中C是光速。光速
distance and the time delay T is given here where C is the speed of light. Speed of light
是一个非常大的数字，意味着时间变化非常小。
is a very big number that means that the time shift is very small.
通常，它是纳秒的量级。这个过程在每一个都被复制
Typically, it's of the order of nano seconds. This process is replicated at every single
场景中的像素。因此，我们需要一种非常特殊的成像传感器。一个不仅仅是
pixel in the scene. So, we need a very special sort of imaging sensor. One that's not just
响应入射光的强度，但响应相位的像素
responsive to the intensity of the incoming light but a pixel that is responsive to phase
转移。因此，这些相机需要非常特殊的感应
shift. So, these cameras require very special sensing
芯片通常没有特别高的分辨率，可能是64乘64像素或
chips and typically, don't have particularly high resolution, maybe 64 by 64 pixels or
128x128.这种传感器和Kinect传感器的一般缺点
128 by 128. A generic disadvantage of this kind of sensor and also the Kinect Sensor
是因为他们依靠将光投射到场景上。这意味着它们不起作用
is that they rely on projecting light onto the scene. This means that they don't work
特别好的户外，你有一个非常明亮的太阳完全压倒了
particularly well outdoors where you've got a very bright sun completely overwhelms the
传感器试图投射到场景上的光线。
light that the sensor is trying to project onto the scene.
然而，它们在室内工作非常好，而且在晚上工作非常好
They do, however, work very very well indoors and they work very very well at night where
传统的相机什么都不会返回。
a traditional camera will return nothing.